( music playing )
Duncan Muggoch:
Although this is TV,
it's TV in a scale that
is beyond anything else.
Peter Welter Soler:
It's the most successful TV
show in the world right now.
It is special.
Very, very special.
Chris Newman:
Today we're shooting
in Croatia,
they're shooting
in Belfast,
and they're preparing
for shooting in Seville
down in Spain.
Whatever hand you're dealt,
you have to go with it
because the show
can't stop.
Bernie Caulfield:
I think we're the only ones
in the world
that shoot
with two units
at the same time
all season long.
If one of those spokes
in the wheel are missing,
it's gonna collapse.
Director:
And, action!
( crowd cheering )
Morning.
How are you all?
My name is Duncan Muggoch
and I'm the UK line producer
for Croatia and Spain,
or what we also call
the southern locations
for "Game of Thrones"
season five.
This is my second season.
I did Croatia last year.
And this year
we've obviously got Spain
thrown into it as well.
So I'm line producing
both of them this year.
And even though
last year was big,
this one's even bigger.
My name is Chris Newman.
I'm one of the producers
on "Game of Thrones."
I fulfill a function
here of planning how
the two units work
and drift in between
the sets, the locations,
and the different countries.
So how was yesterday?
All right?
- Yes. Yeah, it was good.
It was really good, yeah.
- Yes? Good.
Newman:
We start shooting
at the end of July.
99% of the crew
have been here before.
So when you start day one,
it feels like day 301
in a good way.
As this is going on here,
over in Spain
we have Peter
who runs Fresco Films.
He's new to this year,
so he doesn't know quite
how manic it can get.
My name is
Peter Welter Soler.
I'm the Spanish line producer
on this show.
The production booklets,
are we getting them tonight?
Welter Soler:
We have two weeks left
before everybody arrives.
And then two days later,
we start shooting.
I'd be lying
if I said the stress level
is not increasing,
because obviously
this is very important
for all of us.
Doing it for the first time,
we want to please everybody.
We want to do a great job.
This is actually maybe not
the calm before the storm.
It is the rehearsal
before the show.
( chuckles )
We're heading from our
unit base into Dubrovnik,
into the old town.
Filming here
is quite different
from filming in Belfast
'cause the logistics over here
are very different.
One of the logistical
problems of Dubrovnik
is it's such a tight,
small, old city
that we can't get
our big vehicles actually
into the town
just 'cause the streets
are so narrow.
It's just one
of the challenges
that we face
filming in a city
like this.
You can't take vehicles
within the old walls,
so everything has
to get taken by Sherpas
up to a location today
which is probably
one of the furthest
and trickiest you could
get to in the whole city.
A little rule that I have
for myself on location,
and this is never go up
empty-handed or come down
empty-handed.
Now it's just a load of stairs
all the way up to the top.
Hello, gorgeous.
Good. Good, good.
Muggoch:
The principal actors
are just arriving on set
to rehearse.
They will do a rehearsal
with the director first,
and then they'll do
a full crew rehearsal,
which is when they'll place
where the cameras are gonna go
and everything like that.
Man:
Okay, guys, give us
the set, please.
Hey, Joseph.
How are you?
Nice to see you.
Newman:
Episode one and two
have been in Croatia.
They've done most
of their filming and they're
back here finishing up
now that Emilia
has finished in Croatia.
( growling )
- Do that.
Just growl at one point.
- ( growls )
So this morning,
episode one and two
with Mike Slovis directing
are setting up to do
their first scene this season
in Dany's penthouse.
Morning, everybody.
Hello.
Newman:
So it's right at the beginning
of the-- season five
and it's the first time
Dany gets an inkling
of what's going on in Meereen
under her new rule.
And then do you want it
to be a boom,
I've decided
I will not have them?
Or do you want it
to be kind of like--
- No, I think
it's more gentle.
- It's gentle?
It is gentle?
Okay, lovely. Yeah.
I have shot
mostly in Belfast.
I have shot several days
in Croatia
and I am going to shoot
in Seville.
Teach them a better way.
It sounds like something
Jorah would have said.
Slovis:
Moving to a foreign
country on this show
is not as disruptive
as you might think
because one
of the two crews
that you've already
worked with here goes there.
So the first thing that happens
when you walk on the set
is that you see
familiar faces.
Kay Bilk:
My priority today
is looking after Emilia
because she's come
from Croatia,
so we're matching continuity
to that country.
They send
their photos to us
so that we can do the same
as they've been doing.
Rosalia Culora:
There's two departments
filming at the same time,
so it's imperative
that things like wigs,
continuity photos
all travel together
and that every member
of the team is aware
of what the look is,
because if we do
have to take over
someone's artist,
we know exactly
what we're doing
and there's no mess-ups
when we're watching
the show, hopefully.
Slovis:
Let's do one
for camera, please.
Okay.
Man:
Let's have it quiet
for rehearsal, please.
And that means everybody
in here, thank you.
Action.
So the only thing
that gave him pride
was knowing
there was someone
lower than he was.
- Morning.
- How are you?
- Good.
- Morning, Duncan.
Morning, Mr. Muggoch.
- Morning.
Oh, I want
to talk to Peter today
or maybe you can.
Peter Welter?
Yeah, no, I'm talking
with him.
About Córdoba bridge
and the drone.
Muggoch:
As far as I'm concerned,
Bernie is "Game of Thrones."
I've never met a producer
that cares for a crew
as much as she does.
She's an incredible woman
to work for, actually,
and everybody loves her.
And she keeps
everything together.
And do they want
to clear a place
in that?
So the bridge
has to be closed.
That's--
I'm checking on.
Along with David and Dan,
she's the executive producer.
David and Dan
are obviously-- you know,
they're the creators of it.
It's their baby.
Bernie is the one that keeps
this show running.
Sometimes David and Dan
will be with us.
Sometimes they are separate
so that they can both
be on the set,
depending
what the scene might be,
will watch rehearsal,
give their notes on the scene,
and then a lot
of times we're discussing
what is in advance.
As you can imagine,
with 10 episodes,
that we're
constantly prepping.
Much like our
characters, we will go
from the amazing Daznak
right into
the amazing Hardhome.
Caulfield:
I usually have a nice list
for them every day.
They almost cringe
when they see me starting
to come towards them
and open my book to start
asking my questions.
But they're fantastically
collaborative with all of us.
Today, they're having
a big Hardhome meeting
up in Belfast.
- They got the notes?
- Yes. Yeah.
Caulfield:
When we're shooting
in different countries,
it's about a constant
communication
between the producers
in each country.
I'm gonna follow Nutter
over to Spain early.
You're staying here
through Illyrio's, right?
Are we doing a charter
to Sevilla?
We are, yes,
but I'm going to
leave ahead of time.
Yeah, which goes
on the 8th.
I'll go on the charter
this time.
- Hope there's a seat for me.
- There'll be a seat for you.
You can have
Bernie's seat.
( laughs )
In a week, we will all
take off in a charter
to go to Spain and that is now
starting to come very close.
After they have
their big scout today,
then we'll have
more information
to go off of for that.
( birds chirping )
Welter Soler:
We're in the royal palaces
of Seville
called the Real Alcázar,
which are palaces built
by Peter the Horrible
in the 13th century.
It's one of the most visited
monuments in Spain.
The Alcázar will be, like,
the water gardens of Dorne.
Since Dorne is a new world
that's just come into
the show--
it was introduced
in the fourth season,
but we didn't
really see it--
now in the fifth season,
they will finally get to see
the Kingdom of Dorne.
- ( speaking Spanish )
- Good morning once again.
Welter Soler:
It is difficult to shoot
in a place like that
because it was obviously
not built as a set,
but built for a purpose,
a different purpose than ours.
( speaking Spanish )
Some of the places,
as you see in the balcony,
for instance,
I mean, you can't possibly
get some of the gear up there
because the staircase
is too narrow.
So we have to get
a crane in--
Genie Booms, cranes,
platforms--
in order to haul
that material up there.
( speaking Spanish )
- It's tricky, you know?
- Okay.
It's not like
a back lot studio shoot.
First and second
shooting day is up here.
And then we move down
to the garden.
We'll get control
of the garden,
I'm assuming?
As far as you told me,
we have the entire garden
area for us, correct?
- Yes, I have this note here.
- It's pretty amazing.
Welter Soler: They have,
like, an average of 8,000
tourists in here every day.
To see it, like, empty
and have it just for us
is just a privilege.
Wherever you go, there's always
gonna be a challenge
because you're in
a new place both culturally
and logistically.
We'll have to find
a compromise
where we can work
together with the palace.
We're the foreigners
coming into their country,
trying to put
this project together.
I have to say they're being
extremely nice,
which is-- so we need
to make sure that our--
which they always are--
but our crew are very careful
in this delicate location.
Welter Soler;
And what they're doing
for us is unique as well.
It's never been locked off
like this for anybody.
All right, so will you go
and check the others?
- Sure.
- Because I think we're
running a bit late now.
We're now driving up
to a little village
called Magheramorne
in which there is
a quarry that's been there
for a number of years now.
And in season one
we built the set
of Castle Black there.
Because there's a lake
in the quarry,
in season two
we built the battlements
of King's Landing
for the Battle
of Blackwater
with Stannis's boats
attacking.
It's still standing,
although it's looking
a bit worn these days.
Now we're driving up
to have a look at a set
mid-construction
of a fishing village
set north of the Wall.
We'll begin to see
how that's taking shape
this morning.
The set that we see
down here,
it's a fishing village
that is a protected
fishing village.
It's not a military
establishment.
It was designed to be
somewhere where people
had a living off the sea.
So we needed the water,
which is why we put it
on the edge
of the reservoir here.
The fantastic thing
about the Hardhome set
is we're building something
that is so far north this time
that what we get to do
is create a fishing village
that is exactly
as the name describes.
It's Hardhome.
What we've been doing
both in concepts
and in models
is looking at the location
out in Magheramorne
and created what we need
for the action,
which is a longhouse
in which a lot of action
takes place.
And then we have
the landing area,
which we're able to use
the lake that exists
in Magheramorne.
And so through
having those sort of
necessary requirements,
we can then build
this sort of tent city
that will be created
out there.
So I had this good idea,
which I need
to pitch, I guess,
which is to hold
onto that shot.
Miguel Sapochnik:
The director can now see
the bones of the whole set,
so he's gonna walk through
the set and start mapping out
where all the things that
he's imagined will take place.
If the plan to do that shot--
it's the boater's
point of view,
so it's looking
through the fence.
Sapochnik:
So anything at this point
that the director
would like to change,
this is the time that he has
to turn around and say,
"Well, could I put the door
in the hut over here?"
and, "Could I have this
a bit higher?" or so on.
Good, so, yeah,
we good with this?
- Yeah.
- Rock and roll, so...
- shall we have a look...
- Look at this edge here
and see if that works.
Newman:
"Game of Thrones"
is a big event,
and what you mustn't do
is get put off
by the bigness of it.
The thing to do
is to come in and say,
"All I've got to worry about
is the 16x9.
What's in that frame."
It must be like parachuting.
Don't worry about
the height you're jumping,
just make sure
the parachute works.
( crew chatting )
It doesn't have
to be a sparrow.
Muggoch:
Today we've got about
128 extras out
and then everything
that goes with that,
which is the extra hair people,
makeup people,
costume people that have
to deal with all of that.
Nina Ayres:
Crowds start dressing
about 5:00 this morning.
And then just in conjunction
with hair and makeup,
we're just sort of working
around each other.
And then everybody
travelled to set about 7:30
to be all set for 8:00.
Just need to take
your blankets off, guys,
so we can look
at your costumes, please.
Muggoch:
Mark Mylod is the director,
and he's now going
to select the extras
that he wants to feature
in the scene.
Yep, this gentleman.
And one other lady.
It changed a bit this morning
because people had to look
a bit poorer than
we'd originally intended.
I'd just like to maybe
darken a couple of teeth
or something.
A bit of the teeth black,
you know, just one
or two of those.
And maybe-- okay,
the skin's pretty good.
Just a little
less healthy.
And so it was a bit
of a scramble trying
to get everybody
broken down enough
to look a bit poorer
than they had done.
And it's still happening.
People are still
getting dirtied up
as we speak.
- Thank you, guys.
Well done.
- Brilliant.
- Thank you.
See you soon.
We had more than
86,000 applications
to be a background extra
in the show.
People from
not only all over Spain,
but all over Europe,
even from California,
from Argentina,
from South Africa,
wanting to come
to the casting,
wanting to be part
of "Game of Thrones."
- Hello.
- How are you?
- Good.
- Peter. Buenos días.
- Buenos días.
- Buenas tardes.
- Oh, buenas tardes.
- Buenas tardes
is the afternoon.
Maybe you just got up.
I just had a siesta.
- Okay, then it's
good morning again.
- Thank you.
There's gonna be
about 1,000 costumes
to do 600 extras.
Stephen O'Rawe:
Because it's such
a major operation,
we're doing something
like 50, 60 fittings a day,
which normally we do 30.
We fit everybody here,
males, females, in and out.
We do guards, slaves.
There's a rogue slave.
Welter Soler:
There's a slave over there.
Hello, slave.
O'Rawe:
They process down here
and these guys
put on the hair.
Jenny puts on makeup
and they do their magic.
We're moving around
very quickly.
We're shooting in three
or four different places
all straight
after each other.
But we, like, have to go
in advance and prep
600, 700 people
all ready for a camera
that moves behind us.
We're basically set here.
I like when things
are just smooth.
Muggoch:
We've got Lena Headey
and Jonathan Pryce today.
We're shooting a scene here
from episode three
which is what we're calling
the soup kitchen,
which is a kind of
rundown area
behind the Sept of Baelor.
And it's a scene
where Cersei is looking
to have a conversation
with the High Sparrow
who is a whole new
character.
We've got
a beautiful courtyard
which is actually
a former convent.
And we are disguising it
with a lot of awnings
and a lot of ground cover
on the floor.
And it's supposed to be
a really shocking place
where Cersei encounters
the poverty
that she has managed to ignore
for most of her time
living in King's Landing.
I'm standing there
looking butch and macho.
- I do a lot of that.
- Man: Can you show us?
- That's it. That's it.
- There's no...
- No jiggling?
- No, that's it.
If I jiggle, I sound
like "Jingle Bells."
So I can't actually move.
I'm not allowed to move.
I have to stand still.
Muggoch:
From walking about,
we're in every street there is.
It's only started
a few days ago,
so we haven't been here
long enough yet
to really cause chaos,
but it'll come.
Dubrovnik is understandably
a big tourist attraction,
so you're normally fighting
through the crowds.
That's been a difficulty
on the sets.
Rolling!
Nice and quiet.
( speaks Croatian )
- Roll camera.
- Rolling!
- Sound speed.
17, take one,
C marker only.
And, action!
I don't think this is
a good idea, Your Grace.
Nonsense, Ser Meryn.
These are deeply
religious people.
Where can I find
the High Sparrow?
( man coughs )
- Director: Cut. Cut.
- Man: Cut!
- Why did you do that?
- I don't believe you did that!
Are you all right?
- Wanker.
- That's it,
we're on strike.
No, we're on strike.
Fuck you. Go on.
You get into
the fucking pelican.
See how you like it.
( groans )
( coughs )
No?
- Cut.
- You know what?
I can't even lift--
I can't lift my arm
- 'cause it's like a T-rex.
- Hit me, come on.
You think you're
fucking tough?
Come on.
Come on, harder.
( bell tolling )
Newman:
Belfast remains the heart
of the whole thing.
It's a major city,
so we have all the things
that a big film crew need.
But, you know, you drive
20 minutes out of the city
and you're in the heart
of the countryside.
It helps with the ancient
feel of the show
that the landscape has
a feeling of being old.
It's been worn down
and eroded.
And everything has
that ancient feel to it
no matter where you go.
You know, the woods feel old,
the cliff tops feel old,
and the moorlands
certainly look old,
you know.
I always like to go
to the set every day
because that's been
my heart.
This is my 40th year
in the film business
and my heart has always
been in making a film.
I've always loved the set.
You can always kind of tell
how the day is going
by the way Chris
is standing and looking
at everyone around set.
( laughing )
Newman:
I have no idea.
Some of them look at my face
and think if it's looking
very long, we must be
in trouble,
but that's not the case.
I might be thinking about
something entirely different.
I always find him
very calm and very relaxed
given that he's producing
this massive, epic show.
Newman:
We shoot this year
120 days.
But in those 120 days,
we do shoot two units,
so you double it.
You're effectively shooting
240 days of screen time.
( speaking Valyrian )
Today on set
I'm mostly concerned
with the Valyrian.
We have a scene
with the Valyrian language in,
so I'm looking after
the actors
and making sure
that they feel comfortable
with their lines.
'Cause some
of the sounds are quite
tricky to get through.
Director:
All right, guys.
Here we go. Shooting.
Let's have it quiet.
Let's roll cameras, please.
Man:
Rolling.
Director:
Action.
I didn't conquer them.
Their own people did.
( man speaking Valyrian )
( speaking Valyrian )
Find the men who did this
and bring them to me.
- Your Grace.
- And cut it.
Let's go one more time.
Hey, Sean, I think...
Welter Soler:
Right now, we are
in a town called Osuna.
And it has this
beautiful old bull ring
and it's a national
monument as well.
When we walked
into this bull ring,
it was just the place
they were looking for.
The stone is quite similar
to the stone they have
shot in Croatia.
- Made some great progress.
- Yes.
Welter Soler:
This does not have
to be a bull ring.
It needs to be something
completely different,
and that's why we need
to transform it into
that place.
Building the balcony
where the actors are going
to go to the ground.
We had to cover up
all the pillars.
There will be a lot
of things added to that.
We're shooting just one
single scene in here
and it's 12 days.
It's quite complex.
There's a lot
of action happening
and we need that time.
The pressure is so high
to meet the expectancies
of what is involved
in there.
It was just incredible.
All right, ladies and gents,
thank you very much.
- That's a wrap for today.
- ( bell rings )
Quiet down, people.
Listen, clear the cameras,
clear the lights,
the equipment.
Newman:
Here was a very stable,
interesting day
for the character Daenerys.
And then, of course,
we had the big trip out
to see the set of Hardhome
and it did open up
a lot of questions
which will continue to be
looked at in weeks to come.
You do the best you can,
get everything as ready
as you can,
and then you cross
your fingers.
Caulfield:
Today went very well.
We finished our work.
David and Dan were happy,
which is always
my goal of the day
when they come out
with a smile.
Chris and I will talk
and compare notes.
Another two days down.
That's the beauty of shooting
two units every day.
It's the only job
that can live two
days in one.
( laughs )
Muggoch:
At the moment, the main thing
I'm thinking about
is getting out of Croatia.
We've got a lot of stuff
to move to Spain,
so that's where all
my thought is going
at the moment.
And obviously trying to set up
Spain at the same time.
Yeah.
And getting through
every day of filming.
( chuckles )
And knowing that there's
big scenes coming up.
- Yeah.
- Man: So it doesn't stop?
No, it doesn't stop, no.
Welter Soler:
Every day there are things
that you don't expect.
Not having shot with
any of the crew before
obviously increases
the stress level.
- Hello, Croatia.
- Muggoch: Hello, Spain.
So, how is it
all going?
Welter Soler:
As much as the shooting date
is moving closer
and everybody is aware
more and more of the fact
that we have less time,
yeah, stress level
is increasing.
Definitely.
Welter Soler:
Production arriving
in the past 10 days
was actually very good.
There was a lot
of people rolling up.
There's probably 450 people
working behind the camera.
Director:
All right, let's roll
cameras, please.
- Man: Rolling!
- Man #2: Let's roll camera!
- ( clapper snaps )
- Director: And background
action.
Welter Soler:
The first day of shooting
is always crucial to us
because it shows us
if everything we did
in order to prepare it
was the right thing.
( crowd cheering )
( shouting )
Director:
Okay, here we go.
And, action!
( shouting )
This year, Belfast has got
some big sets like Hardhome
and the art department
and construction have done
a really great job
of turning what was a notion
into reality.
( music playing )